Guide to the Frederick Fried Coney Island collection
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Personal Papers and Ephemera, 1870-2000 undated
  - Subseries III.1: Coney Island History Papers, 1870-2000 undated
    - Frederick Fried and Estate of Frederick Fried papers, 1952-2000
      - Department of Parks, City of New York; The Improvement of Coney Island, Rockaway, and South Beaches (City of New York: New York: 1937) (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Ephemera, 1881-1964 undated
      - Two business cards for Melville Langhans, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Tickets and passes, 1893-1964 undated
        - 12-ticket pass to Steeplechase Park (Coney Island, Brooklyn), undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
        - William F. Mangels’ season passes for Schenck Brothers Palisades Amusement Park (Fort Lee, New Jersey), 1912 1917 1919-1924 1931 1938 (Box 13, Folder 1)
        - Frederick Fried’s press pass for Astroland, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 1)
        - Season passes for Dreamland Park (Coney Island, Brooklyn), 1929-1930 (Box 13, Folder 1)
        - Ticket to the Gravesend Hook and Ladder Company social (Gravesend, Long Island), 1893 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Two photographic prints labeled “Roi du Rome” and “Princesses de Galles”, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - One photographic print of a rowboat in an unidentified location, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Postcards depicting Auburn, Maine; Boston, Massachusetts; Ticonderoga, New York; and Youngstown, Ohio, 1907-1927 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Photographic postcard of “Fighting Flames” amusement at Dreamland (Coney Island, Brooklyn), undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Photographic postcard of the entrance to Dreamland (Coney Island, Brooklyn), undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Clipping of “Milch [sic] Cows” pasted to board, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Pamphlets, Brochures and Programs, 1881-1907 undated
      - Pamphlet, Souvenir of Thompson’s Patent Scenic Rail Road Midwinter Fair (San Francisco, California), undated [water damaged, half of back cover missing] (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Louis Glaser’s Souvenir Album of Coney Island(New York: Wittemann Brothers, 1881) [pages detached] (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Annual report booklet, L.A. Thompson Scenic Railway Company of New York, 1902 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Coney Island and Brooklyn, New York, Illustrated, undated [circa 1905 ?] (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Official program, Coney Island Jockey Club, 1899 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Official program, Brooklyn Jockey Club, September 17, 1907 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Official program, Brooklyn Jockey Club, September 24, 1907 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Official program, Metropolitan Jockey Club, October 22, 1907 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Advertisements and miscellaneous, 1879-1905 undated
      - Chromolithograph flyer, Beautiful Steeplechase Island (Bridgeport, Connecticut), 1905 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Frash & Company’s champagne pavilion (West Brighton Beach, New York), 1879 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Book cover for Hildegarde Hoyt Swift’s North Star Shining:A Pictorial History of the American Negro, illustrated by Lyn Ward, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Two empty envelopes addressed to William F. Mangels and Frederick Fried (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Advertisements and miscellaneous, 1879-1905 undated
      - Chromolithograph flyer, Beautiful Steeplechase Island (Bridgeport, Connecticut), 1905 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Frash & Company’s champagne pavilion (West Brighton Beach, New York), 1879 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Book cover for Hildegarde Hoyt Swift’s North Star Shining:A Pictorial History of the American Negro, illustrated by Lyn Ward, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Two empty envelopes addressed to William F. Mangels and Frederick Fried (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Sales correspondence regarding Columbia Gardens Amusement Park (Butte, Montana), 1915-1930 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Visual material file, 1903-1975 undated
      - Photographic negative of Feltman’s carousel dismantled, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Aerial photograph of Coney Island, 1903 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Envelope labeled “Mr. Mangels’ picture of building design,” undated [empty] (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Design for a mechanical horse, ink on paper, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Photograph of Ocean Parkway Baths, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Photograph of bathing pavilion, exterior, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Photograph of swing ride [“from William F. Mangels’ files,”] undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Four photographs of a Mangels/Illions carousel owned by Carol and Harry Koch, King Reid Shows (Essex Junction, Vermont), 1975 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Photograph of cake presented to Borough President Riegelman in honor of the first anniversary of the boardwalk, 1924 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Photograph of the entrance to Steeplechase Park, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Photographs and clippings of individuals: (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Gabriel, Carl, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Haase, Hugo, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Kennedy, W.T., undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Mangels, William F., undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Ruprecht, Joseph, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Thompson, Frederick W., undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Booman, H., undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - “Bradwell,” undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Brewster, James W., 1914 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Browning, Charles, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - “Cagney,” undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Custer, L. Luzerne, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Earisher, Frederick, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Hagenhech, Carl, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Humphrey, D.S., undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Maxim, Hiram, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Peterson, William J., undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Stock, John J., undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Strickler, William H., 1930 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Thompson, Frederick W., undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Tilyou, Edward C., undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Van Kannel, Theophilius, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Gumpertz, S.W. (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Reynold, H. (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Unidentified man, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Coney Island, general view with observation tower, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Dreamland, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Feltman’s Garden (Coney Island, Brooklyn), undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Glaciers, The, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Shoot-the-Chutes, Sea Lion Park (Coney Island, Brooklyn), 1897 [copy print] (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Steeplechase Park (Coney Island), carved lions in situ, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Material related to the L.A. Thompson Scenic Railway Company:
        - “Columbus” amusement, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Delano Gardens, projected view (Saint Louis, Missouri), 1902 (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Flying Dip Scenic Railway (Venice, California), undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Idora Park (Oakland, California), undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - L.A. Thompson Racer (Atlantic City, New Jersey), 1916 (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Over the Rockies (Providence, Rhode Island), 1908 (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Pike’s Peak Railway and Rapids (Coney Island, Brooklyn), 1903 (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - “Razzle-Dazzle, The,” by H.M. Pettit, 1908 (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Scenic Railway, (Santa Cruz, California), undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Scenic Railway (Seattle, Washington), 1909 (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Shoot-the-Chutes in Fairyland, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Tacoma Exposition (Tacoma, Washington), undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Thompson Park (Rockaway Beach) undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Unidentified pavilion, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Unidentified ride, (Venice, California), undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Unidentified ride, “Woodside,” 1912 undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Unidentified park (possible English), undated [in two pieces, affixed to L.A. Thompson letterhead] (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Guest book, American Museum of Public Recreation, 1939-1940 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      (Includes celebrity autographs from Great Garbo, Heddy Lamar, Reginald Marsh, Orson, Welles, and other luminaries)
    - Frederick Fried’s “Coney Island Archive” collection report, 1972-1993 undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
      (The report offers a comprehensive, descriptive inventory of each item in Frederick Fried’s original collection of architectural salvage, artifacts, advertising, photographs, postcards, and ephemera, as well as information about the provenance and history of select material. In 1993 Fried updated the inventory in pencil after a fire destroyed the Vermont barn that housed many of the collection’s large artifacts and sculpture. The volume also includes Fried’s typed and handwritten notes regarding the history of Coney Island’s various attractions.)
    - Negatives and Transparencies, circa 1964 undated
      - Photographs of Hiram Maxim and Theophilius Van Kannell, undated (Photographic prints in Box 13, Folder 7) [Materials smell slightly of vinegar syndrome] (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Painting of Steeplechase Park at the Museum of the City of New York, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Carousel sleigh, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Demolition of Steeplechase Park, circa 1964 undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Subseries III.2: Oversized Volumes, 1880-1976 undated
    This subseries contains items collected by Frederick Fried related to his personal interest in the history of the amusements industry and Coney Island (Brooklyn, New York). Much of this material originally belonged to William F. Mangels and was subsequently purchased by Fried in 1955. Among the items in this subseries are several volumes associated with the W.F. Mangels Company, including a minute book (1908-1959) with certificates of incorporation, company bylaws, and minutes for meetings of the board of directors. Of special note to researchers interested in carousel manufacture and design will be the company’s ledger book, which contains a detailed record of the firm’s client and sales for the period 1908-1915. In addition, five volumes of scrapbooks compiled by Mangels collect articles, clippings, and other ephemera that richly detail the biographies of Coney Island personalities, the history of the amusements industry in Brooklyn, and the programming and collection of the American Museum of Public Recreation. Lastly, this series also contains a scrapbook of material collected by Frederick Fried about Steeplechase Park.
    - Steeplechase Park Scrapbook, 1973-1976 undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
      (Scrapbook containing clippings, correspondence, photographs, and pricing information for party rentals at Steeplechase Park, Coney Island. Item is covered in faux alligator skin and has an attached metal fob decorated with a crest and the words “Coney Island.”)
    - Minute Book, W.F.Mangels Company, 1908-1959 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      (Contains certificates of incorporation, company bylaws, and minutes for meetings of the board of directors for the W.F. Mangels Company.)
    - Ledger Book, W.F. Mangels and Company, 1908-1916 (Box 15)
      (Contains a detailed record of the firm’s clients and sales for the dates 1908-1916 inclusive.)
    - William F. Mangels scrapbooks
      - Volume 1, Correspondence and clippings, 1880-1965 undated (Box 28)
      - [Unidentified volume], Correspondence book, 1934-1950 undated (Box 28)
      - [Unidentified volume], Coney Island scrapbook, 1886-1941 undated (Box 29)
      - “Coney Island Clippings, New and Old,” 1908-1943 undated (Box 29)
      - “Coney Island, Mangel’s [sic] Museum Publicity,” 1884-1939 undated. (Box 29)
        ( In addition to newspaper and publicity clippings, photographs, and other ephemera, this volume includes one folder of historic maps of Coney Island and Gravesend Bay, as well as two renderings of architectural designs for the American Museum of Public Recreation by architects Peter F. Meyer and Edward Schoeppe, undated. )
  - Subseries III.3: Sheet Music and Miscellaneous Ephemera, 1896-1935 undated
    This subseries contains items collected by Frederick Fried related to his personal interest in the history of the amusements industry and Coney Island (Brooklyn, New York). This subseries contains sheet music and sheet music covers for songs whose titles or lyrics refer to Coney Island subjects, such as amusement rides, amusement parks, the boardwalk, and promenading. The subseries also includes other miscellaneous ephemera collected by Frederick Fried, such as two illustrated magazine covers that depict scenes from Coney Island, advertisements for Thomas Edison’s “Electricity Is Life,” and artwork by an unknown artist that depicts two kneeling couples.
    - Illustration of two kneeling [matrimonial?] couples, undated (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Advertisement, Thomas Edison, “Electricity Is Life,” undated (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Sheet Music
      - Afloat on a Five Dollar Note (Arthur J. Lamb and J. Fred Helf), 1906 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - Bamboo Slide Characteristic Marchand Two-Step (Fred A. Cruscaden), 1905 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - Bathing Lesson, The (Joseph Hart), 1902 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - Belle of the Beach, The (Kurt P. Hirsekorn), 1903 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - By the Beautiful Sea (Harold R. Atteridge and Harry Carroll), 1914 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - Coney Island, featured in the motion picture Cain and Mabel (Al Dubin and Harry Warren), 1935 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - Coney Island Washboard (Ned Nestor, Claude Shugart; Hampton Durand and Jerry Adams), 1926 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - Dreamland Waltz (Loula A. Gates), 1905 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - Dreamland Waltzes (William Christopher O’Hare), 1909 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - Just Take Me Down to Wonderland MarchSong (Thos. S. Allen), 1907 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - Luna Park March(J.I. Alexander), 1907 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - Luna Pastimes Marchand Two-Step (Manuel Klein), 1906 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - Mariutch Down at Coney Isle (Harry Von Tilzer), 1906 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - Mariutch Down at Coney Isle (Make a Little Hootch-A Ma Kootch) (Andrew B. Sterling and Harry Von Tilzer), 1907 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - Meet Me Down at Coney Island (Frank Rosenberg and Thomas Dinehart), 1910 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - My Little Coney Isle (Andrew B. Sterling and Harry Von Tilzer), 1902 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - My Little Coney Isle (Harry Von Tilzer), 1903 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - New York Cycle MarchTwo-Step (E.T. Paull), 1896 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - On an Island Surrounded by Girls (Jeff Branen and Arthur Lange), 1916 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - On the Boardwalk (Dick Richards and Newton B. Heims), 1912 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - On the Pier at Dreamland (Edgar Malone and Ted S. Barron), 1906 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - Rock-Rock-Rock, Let Me Rock in My Old Rocking Chair (George Spink), 1907 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - Sweetheart Won’t You Come with Me to Dreamland? (Clarence Manning), 1908 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - Take Her Down to Coney Isle and Giver Her the Air (Ed Rose, George Whiting, and Lew Pollack), 1919 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - Take Me Where I Can Shout (Raymond A. Browne and William H. Penn), 1910 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - Vanity Fair Waltz Song (Stella May hew), 1906 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - Where Do We Go from Here (Geo. Whiting and Ted Snyder), 1908 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - Wonderland Waltz Song (Thos. S. Allen), 1906 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - You’re the Best Little Girl in Dreamland (Ed. Gardenier and Sam Goldie), 1904 (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous Covers, 1909-1924 undated
      - Billboard, The (March20, 1909) (Box 25, Folder 14)
      - Boardwalk Illustrated (Autumn 1924) (Box 25, Folder 14)
      - Thomas A. Edison, Electricity Is Life: Mild Current Good for the Nerves, Cures the Headache, undated (Box 25, Folder 14)